it attracts the most people takes up the
most sare footage if you've never been
would recommend it just understand that
it's one of the most crowded
environments a human being can be in
hotor has got his work cut out for him
but big big training lifts yeah last we
saw him his last training update he was
doing 400 kilos on the Elephant bar
deadlift for triples his classic quad
stomp on top of the stage like bam
striations like I mean that image lives
rentree in my
head welcome to strength weekly the show
that brings you everything you need to
know from around the barbell game and
more I'm one of your Intrepid co-hosts
David Thomas town I'm joined by the
equally Intrepid very smart and can I
say dashingly handsome Phil bman and we
have four hot stories today this is also
the strength weekly dropping right
before right during the Arnold Classic
one of the biggest events in the
calendar year so we're going to get
right to it our first story today is
going to be how to watch all the action
from the Arnold Classic in Columbus then
we have a little preview of someone
returning to competition at the Arnold
Classic for the first time in several
years hawthor bjornson we give an update
on his training and how he's looking
going into his return Jay Cutler
legendary bodybuilder and multitime Mr
Olympia winner will be receiving a
Lifetime Achievement Award at this
year's Arnold and then finally this one
is last week's news but we want to bring
it to you latala God the super
heavyweight champion one of the greatest
weight lers of all time arguably the
greatest super heavyweight withdrew a
rare withdrawal for Lasha from the
European weightlifting championships
fill of these stories which are you most
excited about everything Arnold Classic
I mean if you're not hyped for this show
I mean what are we even doing in the
strength space this is where the
heaviest lifts are going to happen it's
a very very heavy contest for the strong
men and of course we're going to see if
Samson Duda can defend his title against
hotti shupin yeah leardo classic has a
lot of different competitions the
there's the Arnold strongman classic
there's the bodybuilding show there are
functional fitness competitions
powerlifting competitions then there's
the Expo which is the largest by the way
it's the largest event in Fitness in the
world it attracts the most people takes
up the most square footage if you've
never been would recommend it just
understand that it's one of the most
crowded environments a human being can
be in so get ready it is an experience
let me tell you that Phil we're going to
talk a little bit about the actual
competitions today as well as some of
the Expos what is the overarching Wonder
or two sentence thing people need to
know if they want to tune into the
competitive action at this year's Arnold
in Columbus Ohio uniquely this year is a
free way to watch the Arnold uh all of
the Arnold action just go over to the
Arnold sports website and you can just
register and you'll have a free live
stream of all of the action which is
different from past years where you had
to pay to see the action Live Now free
for whoever wants to tune in this is
running from February 29th to March 3rd
it's not like every single lift is going
to be streamed there's a lot happening
and a lot of things will be happening
simultaneously this year's streaming
options free streaming free streaming
seem like they're pretty darn good
especially given the price tag of oh I
don't know free 99 it's presented by the
company bucked up which will be actually
from what we know taking care of and
managing the streaming I feel this is
really interesting it's an interesting
Paradigm for the Arnold to move toward
the fact that it isn't pay-per-view is a
little surprising to me but I got to be
honest pretty welcome yeah I think it's
excellent and it's also going to get
more eyeballs and I think more attention
uh will calibrate to more
in the long term than what the
pay-per-view would in the short term so
I think it's a great move yeah so if you
want to watch the Arnold if you want to
watch the competitions at the Arnold
again the competitive portion it's not
like they're necessarily GNA be live
streaming everything from the Expo just
go to the Arnold Classics website and
you can register you have to register
but after you do you can watch for free
courtesy of bucked up now this is a new
Focus for the Arnold this is a new way
to watch the Arnold remotely we cannot
personally attest to the quality of
these broadcasts of the streaming every
year we tell people how to watch
something even if we're not involved
with it directly and we are not involved
with the streaming directly we get angry
emails and comments from people who
believe that we are the ones streaming
the competition now we have done that in
the past but we have not done that for
the Arnold and we are not doing it for
this year's Arnold so we are excited
that it is free and accessible all you
have to do is register to watch the
action live but we can't attest to the
quality of the streams I hope they're
great I really do but I'm with you folks
so just don't get mad if you know
something cuts out glitches out anything
like that it's not barbon's fault I just
need to get that out of the way I feel
like I have a big weight off my chest oh
feels so good feels so good Phil what
are some of the events you are most
excited to see live streamed and on
which days will they be live streamed oh
and by the way if you click on the link
in the description below uh we have a
more complete schedule of what is
supposedly being live streamed at the
Arnold so click on that link in the
description below and you can sync that
up with your calendar yeah so the actual
Expo lasts from the 29th to the 3rd as
you mentioned but the actual
competitions that are are likely to be
live streamed uh here's a breakdown of
some highlights that you can look
forward to on March 1st we're going to
have the start of the uh strong men and
strong women classic that's day one of
the competition for two days worth of
competition for the uh strong men and
strong women athletes on that same day
there's going to be prejudging for the
fitness the classic physique and the
wellness divisions and then on Saturday
March 2nd that's when we get to see the
bikini the men's physique and the men's
open finals so look out for that
additionally on on the second we'll also
see prejudging and finals for the
wheelchair Arnold Classic that's always
an exciting one as well and then that is
also day two or the finals for the
strong men and the strong women and then
on March 3D even though those
competitions for bodybuilding and strong
men will be concluded on March 3D we
will get to see the Rogue record
Breakers events which are always
exciting because we always see some of
the biggest lifts of the year that take
place as athletes go for World Records
on the big stage yeah and I also want to
point out something that will be live
streamed via limited action is the
animal cage the return of the animal
cage animal supplements uh
sponsors a a cage I mean there's no
other way to put it it's a big cage
where people are lifting crazy things
not so much a competition but really
Elite athletes are invited to come
attempt attempt PRS attempt heavy
doubles triples all sorts of crazy Feats
with barbells in their hands and on
their backs so people get pumped up in
that environment they really really do
so no world records are set in the
animal cage but some unofficial World
Records certainly have been so get
excited there well Phil one person that
we're going to be seeing on the live
stream from the Arnold strongman classic
hofor bson the Icelandic strongman who
by the way won the Arnold strongman
classic three years in a row 2018 2019
2020 he is a former world's strongest
man he took time off to entered the
boxing game became a professional boxer
had a few matches beat Eddie Hall pretty
handily
then went back into the powerlifting
game which he hadn't touched in a while
trained for powerlifting trained to set
some World Records got injured at a
powerlifting event at his own gym in
Iceland recovered and is now back to
professional strongman Phil why is hofor
returning for the Arnold strongman
classic and not the World's Strongest
Man this year yeah so there has been a
uh falling out in the history between uh
hawthor and Giants live due to some uh
discrepancy of a missed rep or should
have been a counted rep uh back when he
lost the 2017 world strongest band Eddie
Hall it was a literally a one rep
difference that made those positions on
the podium there's lots of documentation
of what went down and if you want to
check that out you can it would be a
whole separate episode to get into here
but as a result of that falling out
hathor has said previously that he will
not compete in a giants live event going
forward now of course everything can
change change in the future who knows
what that holds so if they somehow
reconcile that he does have a lifetime
invite he wouldn't need to compete
elsewhere in order to qualify but it
seems like judging from his training
list for the arold strongman classic his
training is actually back up to par with
some of the top athletes now we talked
previously on strength weekly when he
initially claimed that he was going to
return we were like you know it's going
to be tough for him to compete with the
top guys I mean the the caliber of
athlete from where he from when he
retired has very much increased and he's
competing with some of the top guys in
the world in Columbus we're talking
Mitchell Hooper who's the reigning
defending Arnold Classic Champion as
well as the reigning world Strongest Man
Champion we're going to see The Return
of martines Lees who's been very good in
heavy events after a long Hiatus away
you know recovering and he's also been
uh displaying his training on his
YouTube Channel showing how he's been
adapting how he lifts weights as he's
gotten uh stem cell treatment and you
know recovered from previous injuries so
we expect big things from martinz so
haor has got his work cut out for him
but big big training lifts yeah last we
saw him his last training update he was
doing 400 kilos on the Elephant bar
deadlift for triples the Elephant bar
deadlift by the way different kind of
lift it's a longer bar it's a whipper
bar the weight distribution is different
than your standard deadlift bar so it is
an event specific to strongman it is
difficult to compare this to a
traditional deadlift like you might see
in powerlifting it's sort of a strongman
specific event and it's becomes
something we see often associated with
the Arnold strongman classic Rogue
Fitness makes these elephant bars for
that competition Rogue Fitness also
located in Columbus Ohio their equipment
kind of has really come to define a lot
of the events at the Arnold strongman
classic so our prediction is that
overall the competition overall for the
pro strongman hofor finish is probably
just off the podium we could be wrong we
thought he lost a lot of strength he
clearly lost a lot of weight he talked
about this when he moved into boxing and
become lighter more agile and more
athletic in that sport but hey we could
eat our wor we could see a faster leaner
hofor back on the platform doing amazing
things it is worth noting that the
Arnold strongman classic is generally
considered the heaviest event in
strongman world strongest man you're
gonna have to move a little bit it's
thought that athleticism is rewarded a
little more there the Arnold has
traditionally been all about who's the
static monster there's always some
exceptions and I'm not saying all the
events are purely static strength there
is some moving involved but again I'm
still predicting he finishes off the
podium but you know what I'd be kind of
silly to completely count hawthor out
and we'll be bringing you the recap of
that on next week's strength weekly
let's move over to the sport of
bodybuilding Phil when you think Jay
Cutler when you hear the term Jay Cutler
and you think of bodybuilding not the
former Bear's quarterback by the way the
bodybuilder not the quarterback what
comes to mind I mean it's obviously for
me the quad stomp I mean his classic
quad stomp on top of the stage like bam
striations like I mean that image lives
rentree in my head as a fan of uh
bodybuilding and Jay Cutler so that's
what comes to mind for me what comes to
mind for you honestly the Rivalry the
Cutler Coleman rivalry yeah there was
that time where for years uh Ronnie
Coleman seemed unbeatable Jay Cutler
kept finishing in second they had some
epic battles some epic POS downs and now
they're great friends and honestly kind
of a storybook ending because Cutler was
able to finish his career with four
count and four Mr Olympia titles and is
right up there with the greats including
his longtime competitor Ronnie Coleman
uh Jay Cutler I just got to be honest
I've been following him for a long time
on social media dude is hilar ious I
can't wait to hear you know if he's
given time for an acceptance speech I
can't wait to hear what he goes into he
is a fantastic Storyteller Phil what do
you think of this Lifetime Achievement
Award and is Cutler deserving oh he's
more than deserving for sure not only is
like he a four-time champion like you uh
explained but also even in retirement
from the competitive scene he has still
been part of the bodybuilding space as
uh somebody who has his own supplement
line he has a very active YouTube
channel where he shares a bunch of
training content that that helps younger
athletes and Elite athletes learn proper
uh training techniques and like the the
way that he did things when he was at
the top of his game and he's going to
join the likes of uh previous recipients
like Ronnie Coleman and Ken Flex wheeler
I mean he is among the elites and he's
very deserving of this award so it's
it's a great call to put him up there
and uh we're excited to see him on that
stage and I do want to read the ethos
behind the Arnold Lifetime Achievement
Award the Arnold Classic Lifetime
Achievement Award it's presented to
individuals who have made notable
contributions to the fitness industry
and offered a lifetime of service to the
enhancement of sports performance and
promotion and Arnold foregger himself
presents the award every year and look
Cutler he's someone who had a real
narrative to his career and in my
opinion his rivalry with Coleman was a
bit of a miniature golden age in
bodybuilding it was the early YouTube
Days social media hadn't really come to
fruition just yet as we know today but
was just starting to kind of drip out on
various platforms and people were hungry
for content and a lot of what was
driving that content was the Cutler
Coleman rivalry and so for me Jay Cutler
has a special place in my heart because
he's someone I was really following
closely when I was just getting
interested in the barbell game so kudos
to Jay Culler congratulations really
excited to see that award ceremony uh
and to maybe even recap it next week all
right Phil we're going to talk about
someone who will not be at the Arnold
that's George's la Taz the super
heavyweight weightlifter two-time
Olympic champion multi-time world
champion multi-time European Champion I
mean this guy has not lost a competition
since
2015 lha talakad had a rare withdrawal
from the European weightlifting
championships Phil can you give us the
cliff notes on what happened there yeah
so as far as we know it was a minor knee
injury that he was nursing that they
didn't want to aggravate so he withdrew
from the competition now that is notable
because it is unlike Lasha to withdraw
from a competition but they decided to
play it safe it is not going to worry
his qualification for the Paris Olympic
games that is not in question he is
still expected to appear there his coach
pretty funny guy quoted uh saying that
effectively he doesn't want Lasha to
forget what it's like to win which is
hysterical given lha's track record uh
and resume we can still expect to see
him in Paris and in my view I'm sure in
your view in most people's view he's
still going to be the front runner for
the gold yeah and his coach coach Asen
is someone who knows a thing or two
about winning himself an Olympic
champion from back in the day uh the
Georgian weightlifting team has a long
history from the days of khaki Kakashi
through aanad now talakad some of these
top performing men on the international
stages but lha talakad is basically in a
class of his own he was a promising
Junior actually served a doping
suspension a lot of people do forget
about that and took a couple years away
from the international level uh when he
was a very young athlete once that
doping suspension was over he came back
and really burst back onto the scene
around the 2015 World weightlifting
championships which were in Houston now
he originally finished second in that
competition but upon doping test was
actually elevated to First and has not
lost since then and he set some alltime
World Records along the way in the
snatch the clean and jerk and the total
he is Far and Away Far and Away
especially when it comes to the snatch
the greatest super heavy weight lifter
of all time he's kind of in a class of
his own and there's so many other great
super Heavies right now that if talakad
weren't competing May themselves be
ranked among the all-time greats but
they're always competing for second or
at least it seems like they're always
competing for second because tazi takes
such a massive lead coming out of the
snatch that the cleaning jerks I don't
want to say they're easy after that I
don't want to say it's a foregone
conclusion because you have to make your
lifts but everyone's playing catchup and
he puts himself out so far ahead I mean
I remember even just 10 years ago a 210
kilo snatch was going to win you most
World Championships at weightlifting if
you were super heavy at most Olympic
Games or at least get you all the way to
winning most Olympic Games and this
guy's doing 210 for a double in the
training Hall just a few days before
competition so it's a different ball
game with talakad on the platform now we
have seen him slow his role just a
little bit and we've seen him say you
know at one point the 500 kilo total was
within sight now he's saying that's
probably not going to happen in his
career he's 30 years old he's going for
his third Olympic gold medal in Paris
you know he's not making the progress he
once was when he was in his mid 20s it
seemed like every time he took the stage
he'd have a new world record but Phil I
mean is it still safe to say that he is
the odds on favorite in Paris I think if
anybody is able to upend upend him for
the gold medal that would be the in the
biggest Story coming out of the games uh
I still think he's the front runner I
mean the way that we have covered him in
the past to try and convey the the kind
of snatches that you're talking about
are like okay he just threw a grand
piano over his head you know like just
to give context to how heavy the weights
that he loads actually are so I would be
shocked if he doesn't still claim the
gold even if he doesn't get the 500
kilogram total that you know he's been
eyeing for a long time he will be my
pack one pick one draft like gold
medalist out of the games and if he
doesn't somehow do it we're doing an
emergency episode of strength weekly to
talk about what happened and who somehow
beat him because that'll be the story of
the year I mean there are a lot of other
great lifters there a number of lifters
cap who will be in Paris who are capable
of you know snatching 210 clean and
jerking 250 or above my prediction right
now is that we're going to see L snatch
220 in Paris that we're going to see him
clean and jerk 252 kilograms to finish
with a 472 kilogram total for the gold
medal in Paris that is my current
prediction I am happy to be proven wrong
uh I do want to read one quote from
coach aanan uh lha has a minor trauma in
one of his knees and we made this
decision to mitigate the risk as much as
possible possible our objective is Paris
he should retain the feeling of the
podium we're looking to compete in
Thailand to retain that feeling and of
course that's referencing the iwf World
Cup which will occur between now and the
Paris Olympics so we may see lha take
the stage once more before the Paris
Olympics later this year so couple more
chances to see the big guy on the
platform doing crazy things with some
heavy weights well there you have it
folks an exciting week and the last time
you're going to see us before the AR
classic cuz we'll have a lot more to
recap from that next week here on
strength weekly until then I'm David
Thomas to joined by Phil blechman thank
you as always get ready for Arnold
Classic and the Arnold strongman and
strong women classic coverage it's
coming your way on Barb ben.com you
won't want to miss
[Music]
out